Hale Family Papers, 1787-1988
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
The Hale family papers are arranged by generation and then alphabetically by family member. Materials relating to Hale spouses are filed directly following their Hale wife or husband. The amount of material by or about individuals varies considerably from single items to multiple boxes. Where the volume of materials warrants, an individual's papers are grouped into the following categories:
Biographical materials and memorabilia Activities Artwork Correspondence Outgoing Incoming Speeches and writings
In several cases, there is material common to several members of a household, such as both members of a couple, parents and children, or groups of siblings. In these cases, the group's papers are filed together under the household.
Correspondence between family members is filed with the author's materials (e.g., letters BY Ellen Day Hale TO Edward Everett Hale are filed under Ellen Day Hale). Letters by one Hale often contain a short section written by another Hale. These are filed under the primary author.
There is a small amount of unidentified and miscellaneous papers filed at the end of the Hale family materials in box 108.
Following the Hale family papers (in boxes 109-115) is material related to the families of various Hale spouses. This material is filed by family group and then alphabetically by individual. First are the relatives of Emily Baldwin (Perkins) Hale with papers of various Beechers, Gilmans, Hookers, Perkins, and Stowes. These are followed by materials by and about the Everetts and Hills, relatives of Sarah Preston (Everett) Hale. Finally, there are materials related to the Westcotts, Bassets, Clarkes, and Littells, relatives of Lilian Clarke (Westcott) Hale.
Photographs and other visual images are arranged in six groups:
Family Friends and associates Places Subjects Daguerreotypes, tintypes, and cased images Albums
Within the groupings, the images are arranged alphabetically.
Oversize materials are arranged in three groups:
General Artwork Photographs and visual images
Artifacts are filed at the end.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additional Formats
Selections from the Hale Family Papers can be viewed in the Web exhibit Across the Generations: Exploring U.S. History through Family Papers.
Diaries of Ellen Day Hale (1904-05, 1921), and diaries (1850-1862) and commonplace books (1810, 1827-1850) of Sarah Preston Everett Hale are available on the History of Women microfilm series (New Haven: Research Publications) available in Neilson Library, Smith College and through interlibrary loan.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
Nancy Hale donated her family's papers to the Sophia Smith Collection beginning in 1963. Additional materials came from Harriet (Arnold) McKissock in 1997.
Search Terms
Everett, Alexander Hill, 1790-1847--Correspondence; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865--Correspondence; Gaskell, Elizabeth Cleghorn, 1810-1865; Hale, Alexander, 1829-1850--Correspondence; Hale, Arthur, 1859-1939--Correspondence; Hale, Nancy, 1908-; Hale, Nathan, 1755-1776; Hunt, William Morris, 1824-1879--Correspondence; Everett family; Hale family; Boston and Worcester Railroad Corporation--History--Sources; Boston Daily Advertiser--History--Sources; Chesapeake and Ohio Canal (Md. and Washington, D.C.)--History--Sources; Lee Arms Company (Hartford, Conn.)--History--Sources; American wit and humor--Women authors--19th century--Sources; Old and new (Boston, Mass.: 1870) --History--Sources; Old and new (Boston, Mass.: 1870) --History--Sources; Art--Study and teaching--United States--History--Sources; Artists, American--History--Sources; Authors, American--History--19th century--Sources; Boston (Mass.)--History--19th century--Sources; Boston (Mass.)--Newspapers; Children's writings, American--19th century; Clergy--United States--History--Sources; Diplomats--Egypt--History--19th century --Sources; Egypt--Description and travel--Sources; Family--United States--History--Sources; Massachusetts--Politics and government--1775-1865--Sources; Chesapeake and Ohio Canal (Md. and Washington, D.C.)--History--Sources; Hale, Charles, 1831-1882; Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909; Hale, Edward Everett, 1863-1932; Hale, Ellen Day, 1855-1940; Hale, Enoch, 1753-1837; Hale, Herbert Dudley, 1866-1908; Hale, Lilian Westcott, 1880-1963; Hale, Lucretia P. (Lucretia Peabody), 1820-1900; Hale, Nathan, 1818-71; Hale, Philip Leslie, 1865-1931; Hale, Robert Beverly, 1869-1895; Hale, Sarah Everett, 1817-1851; Hale, Sarah Preston Everett, 1796-1866; Hale, Susan, 1833-1910; Westcott, Edward Gardner
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional Hale Family Papers are in the Library of Congress. Additional papers of Enoch Hale are in the Divinity Library at Yale University. Additional papers of Ellen Day Hale, Philip Leslie Hale, and Lilian (Westcott) Hale are housed at the Archives of American Art. Additional papers of Edward Everett Hale and Edward Everett Hale, Jr., are housed in the New York State Library. Records of the Lend A Hand Society, founded by Edward Everett Hale, are in the Massachusetts Historical Society.
Related materials in the Sophia Smith Collection include the papers of Nancy Hale, daughter of Philip Leslie and Lilian (Westcott) Hale, and the Bush-Brown Family Papers.
Appendices
APPENDIX I: Franklin Circulating Library
[see also APPENDIX II: Charlieshope Library]
Proprietors: Alexander Hale, Charles Hale, T.K. Lothrop, Robert Durivage, Edward B. Everett, W. L. Pynchon, H. P. Curtis, S. Willard, E. Everett, Jr., L. Everett [see Volume 187 "History of the Franklin Circulating Library" for information]
1839-40
1 lost
2 A Thanksgiving Tale, Vol. 2 by Petrikin Bogardus, 1839
3-5 lost
6 Metamorphosis by Charles Hale, n.d.
7 lost
8 The History of John by Charles Hale, 1839
9 Picture Book, 1840
10 Story of James and George by Alexander Hale, 1840
11 lost
12 Story of Peter and George, Vol. 1, by Charles Hale, 1841
13 Story of Peter and George, Vol. 2, by Charles Hale, 1841
14 Story of Peter and George, Vol. 3, by Charles Hale, 1841
15 Story of Peter and George, Vol. 4, by Charles Hale, 1841
16 The Celestial Sisters, a Shawnee Tale by ? R. Schoolcraft, transcribed by Edward B. Everett, 1839
1841
17 The History of Jonathan Popp, Vol 1, by one who knew him, 1841
18 The History of Jonathan Popp, Vol 2, by one who knew him, 1841
19 The Story of Jack, Vol. 1, by Charles Hale, 1841
20 The Story of Jack, Vol. 2, by Charles Hale, 1841
21 History of the Crew of the Ship Naumkeag, Vol. 1, Alexander Hale, Editor, 1841
22 History of the Crew of the Ship Naumkeag, Vol. 2, Alexander Hale, Editor, 1841
23 History of the Crew of the Ship Naumkeag, Vol. 3, Alexander Hale, Editor, 1841
24 The Joking Negro by Alexander Hale, 1841
25 The Voyager, Vol. 1, by Alexander Hale, 1841
26 The Voyager, Vol. 2, by Alexander Hale, 1841
27 A Voyage to Patagonia by Charles Hale, 1841
28 The Negro Slave by Robert Durivage, 1841
29 The Bad Boy by Robert Durivage, 1842
30 The French Widow by Robert Durivage, 1841
31 The Agreeable Surprise, an Arabian Tale by Charles? Hale
32 The Picnic Party, or Anna Rose in 3 Volumes, Vol. 1, by the old woman with the Mob Cap, 1842
33 The Picnic Party, or Anna Rose in 3 Volumes, Vol. 2, by the old woman with the Mob Cap, 1842
34 The Picnic Party, or Anna Rose in 3 Volumes, Vol. 3, by the old woman with the Mob Cap, 1842
35 The Humors of Tom King and the Trials of Monsieur Tonson [printed story glued into volume]
36 An Adventure by Charles Hale, 1842
37 Story of Peter and George, Vol. 5, by Charles Hale, 1841
38 Story of Peter and George, Vol. 6, by Charles Hale, 1841
39 Story of Peter and George, Vol. 7, by Charles Hale, 1841
40 Story of Peter and George, Vol. 4 of Second Series, Vol. 8 of First Series, by Charles Hale, 1841
41 A Thanksgiving Tale by Lucretia P. Hale [2 copies, printed], 1840
42 History of Timothy Trumpet and Jack Fiddle by Charles Hale, 1841
43 Various Stories, Vol. 2, by Charles and Alexander Hale, for the year 1840 or 1
1842
44 George by Alexander Hale, 1841
45 Henry by Alexander Hale, 1841
46 Incidents of Travel by Alexander Hale, 1841
47 Queen Boadicea! din'y' ever see her? by Dr. *******, 1841
48 The Old Witch by W. L. Pynchon, 1842
49-52 Story of Peter and George, Vol. 1-4, by Charles Hale, 1842
53-56 Story of Peter and George, Second Series, Vol. 1-4, by Charles Hale, 1842
57 Portraits and Facts by Alexander Hale, 1842
58 The History of the Jack-o-bin Family by a descendent of the race, 1842
59 New Year's Day by Alexander Hale, 1842
60 lost
61 Conundrums and Charades by Charles and Alexander Hale, 1842
62 Adventure at Sea in one volume by Alexander Hale, 1842
63 The Giant by Mrs. Eliza Windemere, 1842
64 The Pirate Ship Hibernian by a member of the Franklin Circulating Library Society, 1842
65 The Journey of Jack and John to Different Places by the author of "Peter and George" [Charles Hale], 1842
66 Bill Pumpkin, Vol. 1, n.d.
67 Bill Pumpkin, Vol. 2, 1842
68-69 lost
70 The Fratricide: A True Story, 1841
71-72 lost
73 The English Cabin Boy by Alexander Hale, 1842
74 lost
75 Extracts from the Log Book of the Ship Ahoy, 1842
76 Adventures of Bill and Tom with Their Dog Jack, Vol. 1, by Charles Hale, 1842
77 Adventures of Bill and Tom with Their Dog Jack, Vol. 2, by Charles Hale, 1842
78 Adventures of Bill and Tom with Their Dog Jack, Vol. 3, by Charles Hale, 1842
79 Adventures of Bill and Tom with Their Dog Jack, Vol. 4, by Charles Hale, 1842
80 lost
81 The Philosopher's Stone by Charles Hale, 1842
82 A Fight by Charles Hale, 1842
1843
83 lost
84 Story of Margy Bindweed, 1843
85 The Chestnut Party with the Adventures which befel the guests on the way there, 1843
86 The Fairy Grasshopper by an unknown friend, 1843
87 lost
88 Curious Anecdote of a Dog by H. P. Curtis, 1843
89 Series of Lives of Cabin Boys No. 1, American Cabin Boy by Charles Hale, 1843
90 Series of Lives of Cabin Boys No. 1, Mexican Cabin Boy by Charles Hale, 1843
89 Series of Lives of Cabin Boys No. 4, Austrian Cabin Boy by Charles Hale, 1843
92-95 Story of Peter and George, Series 5th, Vol. 1-4, 1843
96 lost
97 The Lost Child, Vol. 1, by T. K. Lothrop
98 The Lost Child, Vol. 2, by T. K. Lothrop
99 lost
100 Sketch of the melancholy fate of an exploring expedition. In which all persons perished in the year 1676, 1843
101 Remarkable Bravery by Alexander Hale, 1843
102 Account of Island of Buhe
103 Account of the I[sland] of Mora
104 Account of the I[sland] of Logu, being travels of L. O. Hovey and J. Wright, 1842
105 History of the Island of Logu, No. 1, translated by J. Wright to accompany his "Travels in the Island of Logu"
106 History of the Island of Logu, No. 2, 1843
107 History of the Island of Logu, No. 3, 1843
108 Adventures of Bill and Tom with their Dog Jack, Vol. VI, by Charles Hale, 1843
109 An Anecdote by Mrs. Windemere, 1843
110 The Star by Robert Durivage, 1843
1844
112 Walter and Mindwell or the Deaf and Dumb Quarrel, 1844
113 The Three Princesses, Vol. 1, by Mrs. P.
114 The Three Princesses, Vol. 2
115 The Hawthorn Tree, 1844
117 The Unsuccessful Voyage to American, 1843
118 Settlement of the Island Regia, Vol. 1
119 Settlement of the Island Regia, Vol. 2
120 Settlement of the Island Regia, Vol. 3
121 Story of George and Jack, Vol. 1, 1844
122 Story of James, Vol. 1, Mrs. Eliza Windemere
123 Story of James, Vol. 2
123 Story of James, Vol. 3
125 Visit to the Old Soldier
126-129 lost
130 The Fairy Violet, a Tale by Alexander Hale, 1843
131 Various Stories, Vol. 3, 1844
132 Jemmy and the Bee by Selina Domdoodle, 1844
133 Story of John Harefoot, 1844
135 The Vegetables of Prince Swallowtail, 1843
136-137 lost
138 The Adventures of a Rod, 1844
1845
141 The Enchanted House
142 The Enchanted House, Vol. 2
143 lost
144 Peter Piboo, His Adventure with a Robber and What Happened After It by Robert Durivage, 1845
145 Bill and Tommy. Relating one of their nice adventures!!! by Robert Durivage, 1845
146 Zade Quimee and His Misfortunes by Robert Durivage
147 lost
148 Jack Torkera by Charles Hale
149 The Good Boy and the Bad Boy by Charles Hale, 1845
150 Grandpa's Stories to James, Sarah, Jack, Tommy, and Bobby. Vol. 1: James who wanted to hear about Ancient History
151 Grandpa's Stories to James, Sarah, Jack, Tommy, and Bobby. Vol. 2: Sarah who wanted to hear more about the Adventures of the Trojans &c. &c., 1845
152 Grandpa's Stories to James, Sarah, Jack, Tommy, and Bobby. Vol. 3: Jack who wanted to hear about ships, 1845
153 Grandpa's Stories to James, Sarah, Jack, Tommy, and Bobby. Vol. 4: Tommy who wanted to hear about Fairies, but who heard, finally, about The Lion and Joseph, 1845
154 Grandpa's Stories to James, Sarah, Jack, Tommy, and Bobby. Vol. 5: Bobby who wanted to hear about Dogs, 1845
155 The Water-Party by Mrs. Windemere, 1845
156 The Fairy Procession !!!! by Mrs. Windemere, 1845
157 The Two Birth Days!! by Miss Domdoodle, 1845
158 Daring, and the Giant Man-Eater!!! by Selena Domdoodle, 1845
159 Christmas-Eve or Willie Sherwood by Miss Mudge, 1845
160 The Salamander or Old Grimes, 1845
161 The Block House
162 Life of Wm. B. Jenkins by T. K. Lothrop, 1845
1846
163 Simeon Sykes or the Pearl of Crab Bay, 1846
164 A Complete Set of the Printed Documents of the Franklin Circulating Library, 1845
165 The Princess Moonina or The Haunted House, Vol. 1
166 The Princess Moonina or The Haunted House, Vol. 2
167 The Rocky Well, A Tale of Washingtonville
168 Food for the Young, Second Part
169 The Adventures of Miss Nabby Merrick, a poem by Stephen Tainter, M.D. [printed poem glued into volume]
170 Grandchildren's Stories, Vol. 1, by Charles Hale, 1846
171 Grandchildren's Stories, Vol. 2, by Charles Hale, 1846
172 Grandchildren's Stories, Vol. 3, by Charles Hale, 1846
173 Grandchildren's Stories, Vol. 4, by Charles Hale, 1846
174 Elmiona, or the White Rose, Vol. 1
175 Elmiona, or the White Rose, Vol. 2
176 The Wonderful Swing, A Tale by Mrs. Eliza H.(?) Windemere
177 The Water of Life or Faradae and Banana, Vol. 1
178 The Water of Life or Faradae and Banana, Vol. 2
179 Prince Pomegranite and his Trusty Followers by Jemima K. Quistose(?)
180 One of the Salem Witches, A Tale by T. K. Lothrop
181 Neddy Noodle
182 Aigiokos, The Raven Chief. An Indian Tale by T. K. Lothrop, 1846
183 Little Billy Watson, A Tale by T. K. Lothrop, 1846
184 lost
185 Lost Lillie
186 James Burlot, 1846
187 History of the Franklin Circulating Library from 1838-1846
APPENDIX II: Charlieshope Library
Members: Olivia B. Lowell, Fanny R. Banks, Lucy Parsons, Mabel H. Chapin, Lily White, Mary L. Morse, Nelly Hale, Alice Lee.
The Accident [lost]
Allie and Charley by E. C. Papendick
Araminta by Mrs. Windermere
At Washington, A True Story/The Twins
Book of Fortune by Arthur Hale
The Boy Who Confessed to His Father About the Cat, 1868
The Boy Who Eats Potato and Meat [lost]
The Burnt House by Herman Chapin, 1866
Charley Stanwood/Willie Hyde, 1866
The Crew of the Albatross, Vol. 1, by Mary L. Morse and Ellen Day Hale, 1867
The Day of a Doll [lost]
The Desk Stories, Vol. 1, by Ellen Day Hale
The Desk Stories, Vol. 2, by Ellen Day Hale
The Desk Stories, Vol. 3, by Ellen Day Hale
Ellen Stockbridge/Clara Andrews and Her Friend Who Lived in a Tree by CHL Members
The Faithless Servant and Other Stories by Olivia Lowell
The Fairy Book by Mabel H. Chapin
The Fairy Festival
Fairy Stories, Vol. 1, by Lily Finis Terre
Fairy Stories, Vol. 2, by Lily Finis Terre
The Fairy That Lived in a Tree by L.P.
Fanny Benson by Cynthia Mack, 1866
Flora Hamilton, or the Blackberry Party by Ellen Day Hale
Flossie and Dick, or a Visit to Auntie's, Vol. 1, by Zelle Costello
Flossie and Dick, or a Visit to Auntie's, Vol. 1, by Zelle Costello
The Gold Bracelet by E. W[indemere?]
Harry and Anny âœHarry and Annyâ is an unfinished work from the celebrated pen(cil) of Miss Mary Lesley
The Haunted House by Olivia B. Lowell
Helen's Christmas in Paris/Violet Mason
History of a Button by MLM, 1866
How I Silenced a Dog
Johnny Randolph/Katy Jackson by Ellen Day Hale
Julia Howe
The Lady in Brown, a Fairy Story for Little Children, Vol. 1, by Ellen Day Hale
The Lady in Brown, a Fairy Story for Little Children, Vol. 2, by Ellen Day Hale [only the cover survives]
The Lame Boy
The Lame Boy Recovered
Mary Lee's Visit in the Country
Mary Lowell, or the Desert Island, by Nelly Hale, 1865
Mary Snow and Eleanor Williams âœMary Snow and Eleanor Williamsâ was written seven or eight years ago by a child of six or seven. This must excuse various little inaccuracies of style. [The volume that continues the story is unfortunately lost.]
Novel Without a Name by Arthur Hale and Ellen Day Hale, MDCCCLXVIII
Peggy's Stories, Parts 1, 2, by Ellen Day Hale
Peggy's Stories, Part 4, by Ellen Day Hale
A Poem
The Robe of Lightning, or the Adventures of the Fairy Anza by MLM and Ellen Day Hale
The Six Labourers
The Solitary House in Silo by Ellen Day Hale
Under the Sea
What the Playthings Said to Each Other on Midsummer Night by A Robin. Illustrated by Miss Robina Bright-Eyes
The Young Sportsmen of Vermont by F. E. Peabody
Other volumes not on Charlieshope Library list (published by Morse, Hale & Co.)
The Enchanted House by A. Hale
The Fairy Journey
The History of a Tin Soldier by A. Hale
The Histrey of a Tin Soldier, Vol 2, by A. Hale
The Old Woman Who Lived in the Little White House in the Wood by Ellen Day Hale
The Summer at the Seaside by E.O. [Lily] White
The Visit by E. C. Papendick
Chronicles of Waterford II. Polly's Testimonial by Keren Happuch, 1869
- HALE FAMILY
  - Genealogy
    - General, 1941-67, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Family crest, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Hale Family Association, Beverly (MA) Historical Association, 1991-92 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "The Hales and the Great Rebellion," SSC pamphlet by Daniel Aaron, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Generation I
    - Hale, Enoch (1753-1837)
      - General, 1787-1921 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence: letters to Nathan and Sarah Preston (Everett) Hale [son and daughter-in-law], 1821-31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Hampshire Charitable Society: reports, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Westhampton Congregational Church history, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Will, copy by Philetus Hale [grandson], 1837 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Hale, Octavia (Throop) (1754-1839) [Mrs. Enoch Hale]: deed, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Hale, Nathan (1755-76) [brother of Enoch, "the patriot"]
      - General, 1810-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence: typescript letters to Enoch Hale [brother], 1774-76 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Generation II
    - Hale, Enoch, Jr. (1790-1848)
      - Correspondence, outgoing
        - Hale, Enoch, Sr. [father], 1828-30 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        - Hale, Nathan, Sr. [brother], 1839, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Hale, Nathan (1784-1863) and Sarah Preston (Everett) (1796-1866), Household
      - Family book, circa 1858-78 (Box 2)
      - Family newspapers
        - The Hamiltonian 1841, 1842 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
        - Miscellaneous, 1840, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Franklin Circulating Library (163 volumes): homemade books, mostly by Charles and Alexander Hale
        [See Appendix I for title list]
        - 1839-42 (Box 3)
        - 1843-46 (Box 4)
    - Hale, Nathan, Sr. (1784-1863) and Richard (1792-1839): deeds, Westhampton, MA, 1839 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Hale, Nathan, Sr. (1784-1863)
      - Biographical materials
        - 1804-07 (Box 5, Folder 2)
        - Financial account book, 1849-54 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Activities
        - General, 1815-47, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
        - Boston and Worcester Rail Road Corporation
          - 1827-55, undated (Box 5, Folder 5-17)
          - undated (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
        - Boston, City of, Joint Committee on Public Lands: report, 1853 (Box 6, Folder 3)
        - Boston Weekly Messenger, Boston Weekly Messenger, Boston Miscellany
          - General, 1838, 1842, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
          - Financial, 1835, 1852, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
        - Boston Weekly Messenger: correspondence, 1822-52, undated (Box 6, Folder 6-9)
        - Boston Water Commission, 1845-52, undated (Box 6, Folder 10-11)
        - Chesapeake and Ohio Canal Company
          - Correspondence and reports
            - 1845-50 (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
            - 1851, 1853, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
          - Financial record, Mar-Jul 1850 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        - European Brick Machine Company, 1854-57, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Invention: Improved Stereotype Plate, 1829-30, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
        - Legal practice, 1818-39 (Box 7, Folder 5)
        - Massachusetts Constitutional Convention, 1831 (Box 7, Folder 6)
        - Massachusetts Webster Association, 1848, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
        - Printing business, 1827, 1830 (Box 7, Folder 8)
        - United States northeastern boundary, 1838, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence, outgoing
        - Batchelder, Samuel, 1807-10 (Box 7, Folder 10)
        - Everett, Alexander Hill [brother-in-law], 1818-22, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
        - Everett, Edward [brother-in-law], 1810, 1843 (Box 7, Folder 12)
        - Hale, Charles [son], 1848-59 (Box 7, Folder 13)
        - Hale, Edward Everett [son], 1843-60 (Box 7, Folder 14-15)
        - Hale, Enoch [father], 1817-33 (Box 7, Folder 16-17)
        - Hale, Lucretia [daughter], 1844 (Box 7, Folder 18)
        - Hale, Nathan, Jr. [son], 1840-51 (?) (Box 7, Folder 19)
        - Hale, Sarah Everett [daughter], 1850 (Box 7, Folder 20)
        - Hale, Sarah Preston (Everett) [wife]
          - 1816-50 (Box 7, Folder 21-28)
          - 1851-57 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
        - Hale, Susan [daughter], 1844, 1850 (Box 8, Folder 3)
        - Hurlbut, Martin L., 1810-14 (Box 8, Folder 4)
        - Miscellaneous non-family, 1844-49 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence, incoming
        - Chase, William H. (re death of son Alexander Hale), 1850 (Box 8, Folder 6)
        - Webster, Daniel, 1827-50 (Box 8, Folder 7)
        - Miscellaneous, 1818-51, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Speeches and writings
        - Correspondence and legal papers, 1830, 1850 (Box 8, Folder 9)
        - Notes, fragments, and poems, 1807, 1827, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
        - Address to the Washington Society, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
        - "A Farewell Address to the Students of Phillips Exeter Academy," circa 1807 (Box 8, Folder 12)
        - "Is Party Spirit Beneficial?" undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
        - Treatise on the rail road, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Hale, Sarah Preston Everett (1796-1866) [Mrs. Nathan, Sr.]
      - Biographical materials and memorabilia
        - General, 1810-66, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - Commonplace books
          - 1810, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
          - 1827-51, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence, outgoing
        - Everett, Alexander Hill and Lucretia Orne (Peabody) [brother and sister-in-law], 1811-47 (Box 9, Folder 4-8)
        - Everett, Edward and Charlotte (Brooks) [brother and sister-in-law], 1807-65 (Box 9, Folder 9-22)
        - Everett, William [nephew], 1860-66 (Box 9, Folder 23)
        - Hale groups
          - 1838-47 (Box 9, Folder 24-26)
          - 1848-66 (Box 10, Folder 1-24)
        - Hale, Alexander "Elly" [son], circa 1840s-50 (Box 11, Folder 1-3)
        - Hale, Alexander and Charles (at Harvard) [sons], circa 1846-47 (Box 11, Folder 4)
        - Hale, Charles [son]
          - 1844-1865 (Box 11, Folder 5-30)
          - 1866 (Box 12, Folder 1)
        - Hale, Edward Everett and Emily (Perkins) [son and daughter-in-law]
          - 1836-Apr 1849 (Box 12, Folder 4-12)
          - May 1849-1866 (Box 13, Folder 1-19)